<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
 -->
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
	<properties>
		<title>Clustering</title>
		<author email="solomax@apache.org">
			OpenMeetings Team
		</author>
	</properties>

	<body>
		<section name="Description">
			<p>
				OpenMeetings 2.1 or later is required to use clustering. One database is used for all OpenMeetings 
				servers, so all database tables are shared across OM instances. Certain folders should be shared 
				between all servers to allow access to the files/recording.</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Configuration">
			<ul>
				<li>
					Multiple OM servers should be set up as described in
					<a href="installation.html" target="_blank">
						<b>Installation</b>
					</a>
				</li>
				<li>All servers should be configured to have same Time zone (To avoid
					Schedulers to drop user sessions as outdated)
				</li>
				<li>All servers should be configured to use the same DB</li>
				<li>Servers should be added in Administration -&gt; Servers section</li>
			</ul>
		</section>
		<section name="Database">
			<p>All servers should be configured to use the same database. It can be on the server or on the one node 
			of the cluster.</p> 
			<ul>
				<li>Add users who can connect to the database remotely</li>
				<li>Update <tt>/opt/red5/webapps/openmeetings/WEB-INF/classes/META-INF/persistence.xml</tt>
					set correct server address, login and password. Also add the following section:
					<source><![CDATA[<property name="openjpa.RemoteCommitProvider" value="tcp(Addresses=10.1.1.1;10.1.1.2)" />]]></source>
					Instead of the 10.1.1.1 and 10.1.1.2 set semicolon separated IPs of all nodes of the cluster.
				</li>
			</ul>
		</section>
		<section name="File systems">
			<p>If files and recordings using the same physical folders the files and recordings will be available for 
			each node. You can do this using Samba or NFS, for example. For using NFS do the following:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Install NFS to the data server. In the file <tt>/etc/exports</tt> add the following lines:
					<source>
/opt/red5/webapps/openmeetings/upload 10.1.1.2(rw,sync,no_subtree_check,no_root_squash)
/opt/red5/webapps/openmeetings/streams 10.1.1.2(rw,sync,no_subtree_check,no_root_squash)
					</source>
					Here 10.1.1.2 - is node ip for NFS remote access. Add these lines for all nodes except node with 
					folders.
				</li>
				<li>
					Install NFS common tools to other nodes. In the file <tt>/etc/fstab</tt> do the following:
					<source>
10.1.1.1:/opt/red5/webapps/openmeetings/upload/
/opt/red5/webapps/openmeetings/upload nfs timeo=50,hard,intr
10.1.1.1:/opt/red5/webapps/openmeetings/streams/
/opt/red5/webapps/openmeetings/streams nfs timeo=50,hard,intr
					</source>
					Here 10.1.1.1 – data server ip. And run the command:
					<source>mount -a</source>
				</li>
			</ul> 
		</section>
		<section name="OM nodes configuration">
			<p>In the file <tt>/opt/red5/webapps/openmeetings/WEB-INF/openmeetings-applicationContext.xml</tt>:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					For each node uncomment line:
					<source>
<![CDATA[
<!-- Need to be uncommented and set to the real ID if in cluster mode-->
<property name="serverId" value="1" />
]]>
					</source>
					and input the unique value for each node.
				</li>
				<li> 
					Replace <tt>&lt;ref bean="openmeetings.HashMapStore" /&gt;  &lt;!-- Memory based session cache by default --&gt;</tt><br/>
					with <tt>&lt;ref bean="openmeetings.DatabaseStore" /&gt;</tt> 
					(Currently commented out with following comment: <tt>"The following section should be used in clustering mode"</tt>)
				</li>
			</ul>
		</section>
		<section name="Configuring cluster in Administration">
			<p>Run red5 on each node. Login to the system as admin.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Go to the <tt>Administration -&gt; Users</tt> and create Webservice user (only access via SOAP).</li>
				<li>
					Go to the <tt>Administration -&gt; Servers</tt> and add all cluster nodes with the following settings:
					<source>
Server Name = node name;
Active = check the checkbox. If the checkbox is checked it means node is active and you can use this node;
Server Address = node ip;
HTTP Port = 5080 - port for http part of Openmeetings;
User (SOAP Access) = login of Webservice user from the previous step;
Password = password of Webservise user;
Webapp path = openmeetings - path where OM installed on this node, it would be better if this path will be the same for all nodes;
Protocol = http.
					</source>
				</li> 
			</ul>
			<img src="images/cluster1.png" alt="" width="650" height="461" />
		</section>
		<section name="Ensure everything works as expected">
			<ul>
				<li>Set up the cluster and loggin with two users, go to the same room (also check before room 
				entering that the status page with the room list shows the correct number of participants before 
				entering the room). You should login to the same server initially, the server will redirect you 
				for the conference room to the appropriate server automatically. Both users should be in the same room.
				</li>
				<li>Do the same with only two users but go to _different_ rooms. The calculation should send 
				both users to different servers, cause based on the calculation two different rooms on a cluster 
				with two nodes should go exactly one room for each node. You can now loggin really to node1 
				and node2 of your cluster while those users are loggedin and go to <tt>Administration &gt; Connections</tt>
				and check in the column "servers" where they are located. They should be on different server.
				</li>
			</ul>
			<img src="images/cluster2.png" alt="" width="650" height="369" />
		</section>
	</body>
</document>