<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
 -->
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
	<properties>
		<title>Upgrade</title>
		<author email="dev@openmeetings.apache.org">OpenMeetings Team</author>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Openmeetings Needs Your Support">
			<p>Please take the time to complete this survey:<br/> 
				English: <a href="http://goo.gl/forms/rfuMrwCRC4">Survey in English</a><br/>
				Spanish: <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1STqC3XblHlOJjnfIfBGqQTdj5DQk7qes5rL_UjaxeBg/viewform">Survey in Spanish</a><br/>
			</p>
			<p>As active members of the OpenMeetings community we are asking for your support to implement a broad initiative which focuses 
				on transforming OpenMeetings into a highly reliable and robust open-source video conferencing platform.  
				Like many users we have been frustrated by the pace of development, the quality of documentation, issues 
				surrounding installation, upgrading to the next release, audio and video quality, and reliability.
			</p>
			<p>The goal of this initiative is to ensure the following happens within the near future:</p>
			<ol>
				<li>Maintenance and support for three (3) active demo instances hosted by a reliable vendor such as Amazon 
					Web Services and which includes, at least, visual access to the Administrative Interface.
					<ul>
						<li>The current release - Open to the public and perhaps limited by the number of people allowed in a meeting.</li>
						<li>The next release - Open only to users that agree to help test, committers, and commercial sponsors. 
							The purpose of this environment is to provide a controllable version for which QA testing as a community can be accomplish</li>
						<li>Sandbox for committers to test new code.  Open to Committers and Commercial sponsors.</li>
					</ul>
				</li>
				<li>Organize the community into four groups:
					<ul>
						<li>Users</li>
						<li>Committers</li>
						<li>Testers</li>
						<li>Commercial Sponsors (those who pay a very small monthly fee to gain access and advertising exposure - for example, 
							$10 dollars/euros per month)</li>
					</ul>
				</li>
				<li>Create a system so that donations to the OM Community can easily be made to support the demo environments and to hire 
					engineers to code specific parts of the OM platform to ensure OM stays viable.</li>
				<li>Set formal rules on deciding what features make it into the next release and which plugins and operating systems are to be formally supported.</li>
				<li>Set formal rules on requirements for realizing a new version to include:
					<ul>
						<li>Clear and easy path to upgrade from the previous version</li>
						<li>Robust testing of all features and interfaces</li>
						<li>Capacity/Stress testing</li>
					</ul>
				</li>
				<li>Identify all organizations currently using OM with details about their installation and a up-to-date contact person.</li>
				<li>Ensure that OM is quickly transformed into a 100% HTML5 framework and that all OpenLazlo code is removed.</li>
			</ol>
			<p>We would like your suggestions on how to make OM better and ask that you complete the OM user survey by clicking here.
				Each person who completes the survey will receive the results via email.</p>
			<p>Thank-you for your support.</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
